Finding Aid for the Dena Bat-Yaacov Papers PASC-M.0057
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dena Bat-Yaacov papers
1948-1981
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bat-Yaacov, Dena
PASC-M.0057
1.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Dena Bat-Yaacov (1932-1981) was a concert pianist specializing in the work of Jewish composers, particularly Charles Alkan. Born in Denver, Colorado, she relocated to Los Angeles in her twenties and spent the rest of her life in that city. The collection includes biographical and promotional materials, including publicity photos, some correspondence, and recital programs spanning her performance career.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Dena Bat-Yaacov, 1985.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303623606533
Biography/History
Dena Bat-Yaacov was born Dena Heller in Denver, Colorado, on September 9, 1932. She began piano lessons at age seven, the same year she entered Hebrew school, and made her public debut at thirteen. After attending the University of Colorado, where she studied under Howard Waltz, Bat-Yaacov transferred to the Music Academy of the West in Montecito, California, where she studied with Sarah Compinsky. Later in her career, she studied with Bernardo Segal, Alvin Davis, Edward Auer, and Earle Voorhies.
In 1952 she married Arnold Shevitz in Los Angeles, and the couple had two daughters before divorcing. In 1965 she married again, to Jerome Millman, a Los Angeles physician. The Millmans divorced in 1972.
Throughout the 1960s and 1970s, Bat-Yaacov performed with various chamber music ensembles, as a soloist with orchestras, and in solo recital. She also gave private lessons. After a trip to Israel in 1972, she adopted the name Bat-Yaacov and focused primarily on the work of Jewish composers. Her commentary-recitals were popular with Jewish community groups and at Temple services in Southern California, but she also performed for wider audiences at UCLA and El Camino College. In 1976 she was introduced to the work of French-Jewish composer Charles Alkan, and spent the remainder of her life devoted to mastering Alkan's compositions and raising his public profile through concerts of his work. She began performing all-Alkan recitals in 1979, including concerts at Steinway Hall in Los Angeles and California State University in Fullerton, among others. Dena Bat-Yaacov died in Los Angeles in 1981, at the age of 49.
Scope and Content
Collection materials primarily pertain to Bat-Yaacov's performance career, including biographical and promotional materials, publicity photos, and programs. Programs span three decades and include Bat-Yaacov's early student performances, as well as adult ensemble and solo performances. There is a small amount of correspondence, much of it devoted to arranging concert dates. Also included is Bat-Yaacov's research into Jewish heritage and music, and the composer Charles Alkan, which she related as commentary during her recitals. There is a small amount of personal material including high school yearbooks, a scrapbook, and a few family photographs.
Organization and Arrangement
Collection arranged alphabetically by subject.
Pianists -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Bat-Yaacov, Dena -- Archives; Alkan, Charles-Valentin
- Biographical, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Brandeis-Bardin Institute badge, ca. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Composition for piano by A.J. Brulé, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - Burr, Patricia, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence - Prager, Dennis, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence - miscellaneous incoming, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence - outgoing, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence - performance related, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Israel trip - itinerary and brochures, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Journal, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs - family, ca. 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Photographs - publicity (includes negatives), ca. 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs - publicity, ca. 1960s (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Portrait - drawing, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Programs, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Programs, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Programs, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Programs, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Programs, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Programs - other performers, 1965-1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Publicity, ca. 1960s-1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Research - Jewish Heritage, ca. 1970s (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Research - Charles Alkan, ca. 1970s (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
- Scrapbook, 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Stationery, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Yearbook - East High School, Denver, Colorado, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Yearbook - East High School, Denver, Colorado, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)